<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Blasha]]></title>
  <link href="http://mrikhter.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mrikhter.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-02-12T08:55:35-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://mrikhter.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Masha Rikhter]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Top 4 Motivations for Taking the Leap to Code]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrikhter.github.com/blog/2013/02/12/top-4-motivations-for-taking-the-leap-to-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-12T08:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrikhter.github.com/blog/2013/02/12/top-4-motivations-for-taking-the-leap-to-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Top 4 Motivations for Taking the Leap to Code
My quick and dirty reasoning behind a career change from hedge fund auditor to developer.</p>

<p>Meaningful and Realistic Contributions
After much reflection I came to understand that one of the driving factors of my dissatisfied with my previously chosen career path is the fact that I was a necessary evil. What kind of contribution was that to the world? I want to build! I want to create! As children, many of us spoke of a desire to change the world, which we eventually accepted as unlikely to be realized. With coding, not only is this idea completely within reach, it is limited only by your imagination.</p>

<p>Consistently Evolving Industry
There is no way to know everything there is to know about code. Ever. The thought of a lifetime of learning and growth is incredibly appealing to me. This industry is one which is obviously proactively changing but it is one of few. There is no room for complacency in life and I want my career to be a reflection of this mantra.</p>

<p>The Culture
There is so much to be said for surrounding yourself by the right people, and most people have already said it. I subscribe to the belief that loving what you do is equally important as doing it with good people. Motivated, positive, open-minded and kind people will elevate your mood and in turn your general happiness. The coding culture is also one of sharing and inclusiveness. What more could you ask for?</p>

<p>I Love Puzzles
Seriously, writing code is like solving a super complicated puzzle. Sure it&#8217;s frustrating when you can&#8217;t find that perfectly fitting piece and sure sometimes you try to shove one in that you know doesn&#8217;t fit, but you can&#8217;t deny that giddy sense of accomplishment when it all works out. I want to feel that joy everyday.</p>

<p>Over the next three months, I am eager to uncover philosophical reasons for coding which my mind was not even aware existed.</p>

<p>Are you contemplating taking this leap as well?</p>

<p>If you&#8217;re already there, what were your motivations?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello]]></title>
    <link href="http://mrikhter.github.com/blog/2013/02/06/hello/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-06T11:19:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://mrikhter.github.com/blog/2013/02/06/hello</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
